Picture this:
تصوّر الآتي :
It's Monday morning,
إنه صباح يوم الاثنين ،
you're at the office,
أنت في مكتبك ،
you're settling in for the day at work,
وباقٍ طوال اليوم في مكان العمل ،
and this guy that you sort of recognize from down the hall,
ثم يأتي ذلك الشخص الذي بالكاد تعرفه من نفس الطابق
walks right into your cubicle
ويمر بجانب مكتبك
and he steals your chair.
ثم يسرق كرسيك .
Doesn't say a word —
وبدون أي كلمة ،
just rolls away with it.
يأخذه معه بعيداً .
Doesn't give you any information about why he took your chair
بدون ذكر أي معلومة عن سبب أخذه لكرسيك
out of all the other chairs that are out there.
من بين كل الكراسي الموجودة هناك .
Doesn't acknowledge the fact that you might need your chair
وبدون اهتمام أنك قد تحتاج لكرسيك
to get some work done today.
اليوم لإنجاز بعض العمل .
You wouldn't stand for it. You'd make a stink.
لن تسكت له ، ستحدث ضجة .
You'd follow that guy back to his cubicle
ستلحق بذلك الشخص إلى مكتبه
and you'd say, "Why my chair?"
وتقول ، " لماذا كرسيي ؟ "
Okay, so now it's Tuesday morning and you're at the office,
حسناً ، إنه صباح يوم الثلاثاء وأنت في مكتبك ،
and a meeting invitation pops up in your calendar.
وفجأة ظهرت دعوة حضور اجتماع على جدولك .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
And it's from this woman who you kind of know from down the hall,
من تلك المرأة والتي بالكاد تعرفها من نفس الطابق ،
and the subject line references some project that you heard a little bit about.
وفي العنوان مذكورة بعض المشاريع التي سمعت عنها القليل فقط .
But there's no agenda.
ولكن ليس هناك جدول أعمال .
There's no information about why you were invited to the meeting.
لا يوجد هناك أي معلومة عن سبب دعوتك لحضور الاجتماع .
And yet you accept the meeting invitation, and you go.
ومع ذلك فقد قبلت الدعوة لحضور الاجتماع ، وذهبت .
And when this highly unproductive session is over,
وعندما انتهت تلك الجلسة الغير مثمرة ،
you go back to your desk,
عدت إلى طاولتك ،
and you stand at your desk and you say,
ووقفت إلى جانبها ثم قلت ،
"Boy, I wish I had those two hours back,
" ليتني استطيع استعادة تلك الساعتين ،
like I wish I had my chair back."
كما اتمنى أن أستعيد كرسيي . "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Every day, we allow our coworkers,
يومياً ، نسمح لزملاءنا في العمل ،
who are otherwise very, very nice people,
والذين يعتبرون أشخاص لطفاء جداً ،
to steal from us.
بسرقتنا .
And I'm talking about something far more valuable than office furniture.
أتحدث عن شئ ذو قيمة أكثر من مجرد أثاث المكتب
I'm talking about time. Your time.
أنا أتحدث عن الوقت ، وقتك .
In fact, I believe that
في الواقع ، أعتقد أننا
we are in the middle of a global epidemic
في وسط وباء عالمي
of a terrible new illness known as MAS:
لمرض جديد يُعرف بالمقط :
Mindless Accept Syndrome.
متلازمة القبول الطائش .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
The primary symptom of Mindless Accept Syndrome
أولى أعراض متلازمة القبول الطائش
is just accepting a meeting invitation the minute it pops up in your calendar.
هي قبول دعوة إجتماع فور ظهروها على جدولك .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
It's an involuntary reflex — ding, click, bing — it's in your calendar,
إنه فعل لا إرادي ، دنق ، كليك ، بنق ، وهاهو على جدولك أعمالك ،
"Gotta go, I'm already late for a meeting." (Laughter)
" يجب أن أذهب ، أنا متأخر أصلاً على الاجتماع . " ( ضحك )
Meetings are important, right?
الاجتماعات مهمة ، أليس كذلك ؟
And collaboration is key to the success of any enterprise.
والتعاون هو مفتاح نجاح أي مشروع .
And a well-run meeting can yield really positive, actionable results.
والإجتماع المدار جيداً قد ينتج نتائج إيجابية وفعالة .
But between globalization
لكن بين العولمة
and pervasive information technology,
وتغلغل تكنولوجيا المعلومات .
the way that we work
تغيرت طريقة عملنا
has really changed dramatically over the last few years.
في السنوات الأخيرة الماضية بشكل جذري .
And we're miserable. (Laughter)
ومازلنا بائسين . (ضحك )
And we're miserable not because the other guy can't run a good meeting,
نحن بائسين ليس لأن ذلك الشخص غير قادر على إدارة اجتماع جيد ،
it's because of MAS, our Mindless Accept Syndrome,
بل بسبب المقط ، متلازمة القبول الطائش ،
which is a self-inflicted wound.
الأذى الذي تسببت به لنفسك .
Actually, I have evidence to prove that MAS is a global epidemic.
في الواقع ، لدي دليل يثبت أن المقط وباء عالمي .
Let me tell you why.
دعوني أخبركم السبب .
A couple of years ago, I put a video on Youtube, and in the video,
قبل بضع سنوات ، نشرت فيديو على اليوتيوب ، مثلت فيه
I acted out every terrible conference call you've ever been on.
كل مواقف الإجتماعات المزعجة التي مررتم بها .
It goes on for about five minutes,
مدة ذلك المقطع حوالي 5 دقائق ،
and it has all the things that we hate about really bad meetings.
وفيه كل تلك الأشياء التي نكرهها حقاً عن الإجتماعات السيئة .
There's the moderator who has no idea how to run the meeting.
هنالك رئيس الإجتماع الذي لا يملك أية فكرة عن كيفية إدارة الإجتماع .
There are the participants who have no idea why they're there.
هناك المشاركين الذين لايملكون فكرة عن سبب تواجدهم هناك
The whole thing kind of collapses into this collaborative train wreck.
يبدو وكأن كل شئ ينهار إلى سلسلة حطام تعاوني
And everybody leaves very angry.
ثم يغادر الجميع غاضبون .
It's kind of funny.
ذلك طريف نوعاً ما .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Let's take a quick look.
دعونا نلقي نظرة .
(Video) Our goal today is to come to an agreement on a very important proposal.
(فيديو) هدفنا اليوم أن نتفق على اقتراح هام .
As a group, we need to decide if —
كفريق ، نحتاج أن نقرر اذا ،
bloop bloop —
بلوب بلوب ،
Hi, who just joined?
أهلاً ، من انضم إلينا الآن ؟
Hi, it's Joe. I'm working from home today.
مرحبا ، أنا جو ، أعمل اليوم من المنزل .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Hi, Joe. Thanks for joining us today, great.
أهلاً ، جو ، شكراً لانضمامك معنا اليوم ، رائع .
I was just saying, we have a lot of people on the call we'd like to get through,
كنت أقول ، لدينا الكثير من الناس على الهاتف نرغب بتجاوزهم ،
so let's skip the roll call
لذلك دعونا نتجاوز الاتصالات
and I'm gonna dive right in.
وسأغوص في العمق .
Our goal today is to come to an agreement on a very important proposal.
هدفنا اليوم أن نتفق على اقتراح في موضوع هام جداً .
As a group, we need to decide if —
كفريق ، نحتاج أن نقرر ،
bloop bloop —
بلوب بلوب ،
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Hi, who just joined?
أهلاً ، من انضم إلينا الآن ؟
No? I thought I heard a beep. (Laughter)
لا ؟ حسبت أني قد سمعت رنين . (ضحك)
Sound familiar?
أيبدو ذلك مألوفاً ؟
Yeah, it sounds familiar to me, too.
نعم يبدو مؤلوفاً لي ، أيضاً .
A couple of weeks after I put that online,
بعد أسبوعين من رفع ذلك الفيديو ،
500,000 people in dozens of countries,
500000 شخص من عشرات الدول ،
I mean dozens of countries,
أؤكد من عشرات الدول ،
watched this video.
شاهدوا ذلك الفيديو .
And three years later, it's still getting thousands of views every month.
وبعدها بثلاث سنوات ، مازال يحصد آلاف المشاهدات كل شهر .
It's close to about a million right now.
لقد اقترب من المليون مشاهدة لحد الآن .
And in fact, some of the biggest companies in the world,
في الواقع ، بعض كبرى الشركات في العالم ،
companies that you've heard of but I won't name,
شركات سمعتم عنها ، لن أذكر اسماءها ،
have asked for my permission to use this video in their new-hire training
طلبوا موافقتي لاستخدام الفيديو في تدريب الموظفين الجدد
to teach their new employees how not to run a meeting at their company.
لتعليم موظفيهم الجدد كيف لا يديرون اجتماع في شركتهم .
And if the numbers —
واذا كانت الأعداد ،
there are a million views and it's being used by all these companies —
والمليون مشاهدة ، التي تستخدمها تلك الشركات ،
aren't enough proof that we have a global problem with meetings,
لا تعتبر دليلاً كافياً أن لدينا مشكلة عالمية مع الإجتماعات ،
there are the many, many thousands
فهناك أيضاً آلاف الآلاف
of comments posted online
من التعليقات على الإنترنت
after the video went up.
بعدما انتشر الفيديو .
Thousands of people wrote things like,
آلاف الأشخاص كتبوا تعليقات مثل ،
"OMG, that was my day today!"
" يا الهي ، ذلك تماماً مثل يومي ! "
"That was my day every day!"
" ذلك مثل يومي كل يوم ! "
"This is my life."
" تلك هي حياتي . "
One guy wrote,
شخص ما كتب ،
"It's funny because it's true.
" ذلك طريف لأنه حقيقي .
Eerily, sadly, depressingly true.
حقيقي بشكل مخيف ، محزن ومحبط .
It made me laugh until I cried.
جعلني ذلك أضحك إلى أن بكيت .
And cried. And I cried some more."
وبكيت ، وبكيت كثيراً بعض الشئ . "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
This poor guy said,
شخص مسكين قال ،
"My daily life until retirement or death, sigh."
" هذه هي حياتي اليومية إلى أن أتقاعد أو أموت ، تأوه . "
These are real quotes
كانت تلك اقتباسات حقيقية
and it's real sad.
ومحزنة حقيقةً .
A common theme running through all of these comments online
نمط شائع يشمل كل تلك التعليقات على الإنترنت
is this fundamental belief that we are powerless
هل هذا اعتقاد أساسي بأننا عديمي الحيلة
to do anything other than go to meetings
أن نفعل شيئاً خلاف حضورنا للإجتماعات
and suffer through these poorly run meetings
وأنا نعاني من سير الإجتماعات العقيم
and live to meet another day.
وأن نعيش لنجتمع يوماً آخر .
But the truth is, we're not powerless at all.
لكن الحقيقة ، أننا لسنا عديمي الحيلة
In fact, the cure for MAS is right here in our hands.
في الواقع ، علاج المقط هو هنا بين أيدينا .
It's right at our fingertips, literally.
حرفياً ، على أطراف أصابعنا .
It's something that I call ¡No MAS!
أنه شئ أدعوه بـاللامقط !
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Which, if I remember my high school Spanish,
والذي ، لو كنت أتذكر لغتي الإسبانية في الثانوية
means something like, "Enough already, make it stop!"
يعني شيئاً مثل ، " ما يكفي الآن ، يجعله يتوقف ! "
Here's how No MAS works. It's very simple.
إليكم كيف يعمل اللامقط أنه بسيط للغاية .
First of all, the next time you get a meeting invitation
قبل كل شئ ، المرة القادمة التي تأتيك دعوة للإجتماع
that doesn't have a lot of information in it at all,
بدون أن تحتوي على الكثير من المعلومات أبداً ،
click the tentative button!
اضغط على زر التردد !
It's okay, you're allowed, that's why it's there.
لا تخف ، مسموح لك ، ذلك سبب وجوده أصلاً .
It's right next to the accept button.
يقع بجانب زر القبول .
Or the maybe button, or whatever button is there for you not to accept immediately.
أو زر الإحتمال ، أو أي زر يجعلك لا تقبل مباشرة .
Then, get in touch with the person who asked you to the meeting.
بعدها تواصل من الشخص صاحب الدعوة للإجتماع .
Tell them you're very excited to support their work,
وأخبره أنك متحمس لدعم عملهم ،
ask them what the goal of the meeting is,
وأسأله عن الهدف من الإجتماع ،
and tell them you're interested in learning how you can help them achieve their goal.
وأخبره أنك مهتم بتعلم كيفية مساعدتهم في تحقيق هدفهم .
And if we do this often enough,
لو قمنا بذلك لمدة كافية ،
and we do it respectfully,
وفعلناه باحترام ،
people might start to be a little bit more thoughtful
فقد يبدأ الناس بالتفكير قليلاً
about the way they put together meeting invitations.
في طريقة ترتيب دعوات الإجتماعات .
And you can make more thoughtful decisions about accepting it.
وتستطيع أن تفكرقليلاً في قبولها .
People might actually start sending out agendas. Imagine!
قد يبدأ الناس في إرسال الأجندات ، تخيلوا !
Or they might not have a conference call with 12 people to talk about a status
أو قد لا يضطرون للتواصل مع 12 شخص للتحدث عن أمر
when they could just do a quick email and get it done with.
قد يستطيعون إنجازه بسرعة عن طريق البريد الإلكتروني .
People just might start to change their behavior because you changed yours.
قد يبدأ الناس بتغيير سلوكهم لأنك قمت أنت بتغيير سلوكك .
And they just might bring your chair back, too. (Laughter)
وقد تستعيد كرسيك أيضاً . ( ضحك )
No MAS!
لا مقط !
Thank you.
شكراً لكم .
(Applause).
( تصفيق )